<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.2.0">Jekyll</generator><link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2021-02-20T19:37:02+01:00</updated><id>/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Koen Raijer</title><subtitle>I'm Koen, a med student in rotations from the Netherlands. This is where I write about technology, psychedelics research and mental health, data science, programming, and ethics. 
</subtitle><author><name>Koen Raijer</name><email>koenraijer@protonmail.com</email></author><entry><title type="html">When Peter Singer joins forces with minimalism</title><link href="/philosophy/2021/02/20/Singer-Minimalism.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="When Peter Singer joins forces with minimalism" /><published>2021-02-20T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2021-02-20T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>/philosophy/2021/02/20/Singer-Minimalism</id><content type="html" xml:base="/philosophy/2021/02/20/Singer-Minimalism.html">&lt;p&gt;In Peter Singer’s compelling essay titled &lt;i&gt;Famine, Affluence and Morality&lt;/i&gt;, he argues that most people in affluent countries are &lt;b&gt;morally obliged&lt;/b&gt; to give way more money to charity than they currently do. I previously wrote a &lt;a href=&quot;/philosophy/2020/02/05/Singer-Summary.html&quot;&gt;short summary&lt;/a&gt; of it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The essay does a wonderful job substantiating its point. While many ethical theories are shrouded in vagueness or clouded with jargon, this one is not. It’s easy to understand. THe message is short and powerful.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As much as it is powerful, it is also very awkward. Adhering to Singer’s idea means turning your whole life upside down. If you believe in the truth of this essay but you haven’t &lt;i&gt;acted&lt;/i&gt; on it &lt;b&gt;yet&lt;/b&gt;, every purchase you make will come with a sense of guilt. If you belong to that group, you will probably stay inspired for a couple of weeks. You’ll tell your friends about it, and some of them might also read the essay. Eventually, life will continue as usual. While your mind gets occupied by new ideas, the unease you felt before at the thought of buying new stuff slowly diminishes as you forget about the urgency of Singer’s message.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The above is exactly what happened to me. We need &lt;b&gt;more reason&lt;/b&gt; to buy less stuff &lt;i&gt;permanently&lt;/i&gt;. The problem is that the continuous pull from advertisements which bombard us every moment of the day, is too large for Singer’s essay to resist all by itself. It needs allies.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There happens to be another movement that wants people to buy less stuff. It also needs allies. It’s called &lt;b&gt;minimalism&lt;/b&gt;, and it’s about being more mindful about the stuff you need, and the stuff you don’t. It wants you to ask yourself if you &lt;i&gt;need&lt;/i&gt; this item and if it makes you &lt;i&gt;happy&lt;/i&gt;. That’s a good message in today’s world. 
It came to my attention after watching this (pretty mediocre) &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.imdb.com/title/tt3810760/&quot;&gt;Netflix documentary&lt;/a&gt; in 2015. Around the same time, Marie Kondo got famous for her books on tidying up your house.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Since then, the movement’s motives slowly deteriorated. Slowly but surely, the emphasis shifted from an attitude towards objects, to an aesthetic movement. Instead of trying to live with less stuff, minimalists increasingly urged you to &amp;lt;/i&amp;gt;replace&amp;lt;/i&amp;gt; your current stuff with other stuff that “looks minimal”. Consider the commercial genious behind Marie Kondo. First she tells you to throw away your stuff, only to &lt;a href=&quot;https://konmari.com/&quot;&gt;sell&lt;/a&gt; you her own stuff. Minimalism’s initial, anti-consumerist agenda has been commercialized. Evidently, it couldn’t resist the forces of the advertising industry.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Why did that happen? Consider what happens if you subscribe to the ideas minimalism preaches: you buy less stuff. You’re now left with more money, and you haven’t found a new purpose for it yet. If we make Peter Singer and minimalism join forces, we have found that purpose. We now have a powerful pull away from buying new stuff, and a meaningful purpose for the money we’re left with: charity.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Koen</name></author><category term="Philosophy" /><category term="Philosophy" /><summary type="html">In Peter Singer’s compelling essay titled Famine, Affluence and Morality, he argues that most people in affluent countries are morally obliged to give way more money to charity than they currently do. I previously wrote a short summary of it.</summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Book summary: Peter Singer’s Famine, Affluence and Morality</title><link href="/philosophy/2020/02/05/Singer-Summary.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Book summary: Peter Singer’s Famine, Affluence and Morality" /><published>2020-02-05T00:00:00+01:00</published><updated>2020-02-05T00:00:00+01:00</updated><id>/philosophy/2020/02/05/Singer-Summary</id><content type="html" xml:base="/philosophy/2020/02/05/Singer-Summary.html">&lt;p&gt;This is my summary of Peter Singer’s 1971 essay; Famine, Affluence and Morality. It has brought forth movements like &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.effectivealtruism.org/&quot;&gt;Effective Altruism&lt;/a&gt; and is widely regarded as an important piece of Western ethical thinking. You can read the original essay &lt;a href=&quot;https://personal.lse.ac.uk/ROBERT49/teaching/mm/articles/Singer_1972Famine.pdf&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-main-premise&quot;&gt;The main premise&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The essay was inspired by the famine of regufees that fled after the Bangladesh Liberation War. While millions of people were starving, affluent governments did very little to prevent this. Singer uses this situation as a model to argue that many rich countries’ responses to catastrophes are unjustifiable. I have briefly summarized the premises of his reasoning below.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;div class=&quot;text-box&quot;&gt;

  &lt;ol&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;Dying of starvation is bad.
 &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;If you are able to prevent something bad from happening, without sacrificing anything of comparable moral importance, you ought to do it.&lt;/p&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;You must prevent something bad from happening, unless that would mean causing something comparably bad to happen, or if it would fail to cause something good of comparable weight.&lt;/i&gt; 
 &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;We &lt;b&gt;are&lt;/b&gt; able to prevent the bad thing, without sacrificying anything of comparable moral importance or significance.&lt;/p&gt;

      &lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Lack of food, shelter and medicine can be solved by donating to charity. Many people in affluent Western nations would not need to sacrifice anything important. We can do without the latest electronics, expensive clothing or jewelry if that means preventing someone dying from starvation.&lt;/i&gt;
 &lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
    &lt;li&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;We ought to give to charity maximally, or at least way much more than we do now.
&lt;br /&gt;&lt;br /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
    &lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;the-following-analogy-is-right-on-the-money&quot;&gt;The following analogy is right on the money.&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&quot;If I am walking past a shallow pond and see a child drowning in it, I ought to wade in and pull the child out. This will mean getting my clothes muddy, but this is insignificant, while the death of the child would presumably be a very bad thing.&quot;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The &lt;b&gt;take away&lt;/b&gt; is that it’s just as bad to buy new clothes while a child anywhere in the world is dying of starvation. &lt;i&gt;There is no difference&lt;/i&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;counter-arguments--objections&quot;&gt;Counter arguments + objections.&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have summarized some common objections you might have, and Singer’s answer to them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Even though, &lt;i&gt;psychologically&lt;/i&gt; speaking, we may be less inclined to help someone if they live far away, that is not a valid objection if you accept any principle of impartiality, univeralizability or equality. The most widespread contemporary example of such a principe is &lt;a href=&quot;https://www.un.org/en/universal-declaration-human-rights/index.html&quot;&gt;The Universal Declaration of Human Rights&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It does not matter, either, whether other people are present who are also able to help. Imagine you see a child drowning in a pond in a park full of people, does that excuse you from acting?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many people will never pay their fair share, but that does not excuse you from paying &lt;i&gt;more than your fair share&lt;/i&gt;. Imagine you’re at the pond again. This time, &lt;i&gt;fifty&lt;/i&gt; children are drowning at the same time. You happen to be at a barbecue party with exactly fifty guests. Half of the guests prefer staying clean and dry. Would you comfortably let 25 children &lt;i&gt;drown and die&lt;/i&gt;, knowning you have paid your fair share?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;You may be wondering why you would need to give away money you worked hard for, but the same amount of effort would lead you to be dirt poor in many other parts of the world. Consider the following quote by famous investor Warren Buffet:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&quot;If you stick me down in the middle of Bangladesh or Peru, you'l find out how much this talent is going to produce in the wrong kind of soil.&quot;&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Most of your wealth is not attributable to your efforts, but rather to your place of birth.&lt;/p&gt;</content><author><name>Koen</name></author><category term="Philosophy" /><category term="Philosophy" /><summary type="html">This is my summary of Peter Singer’s 1971 essay; Famine, Affluence and Morality. It has brought forth movements like Effective Altruism and is widely regarded as an important piece of Western ethical thinking. You can read the original essay here.</summary></entry></feed>